A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education and Public Policy Program (EPP), Office of the Vice President, Office Files of Harold Howe II FA538
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Education and Public Policy Program (EPP), Office of the Vice President, Office Files of Harold Howe II
1963-1990, bulk 1971-1980
1971-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Howe, Harold, II (1918-2002)
Ford Foundation
FA538
5.26 Cubic Feet 4 record storage boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Documents the work of Harold Howe II and his broad range of adminstrative, policy, task force, committee and administrative activities including his contributions to the Foundation beyond the EPP.
Biographical / Historical
Harold "Doc" Howe II (1918-2002) was an educator who served as the United States Commissioner of Education between 1965 and 1968. Howe also worked for more than ten years at the Ford Foundation. After working as a Program Advisor in the Foundation's Asia and the Pacific, India and Nepal Program, he became Vice President for the Division of Education and Research. He continued directing the Foundation's education programming when it was reorganized into the Division of Education and Public Policy.
Howe started his career in education after serving in the United States Navy in World War II where he was a minesweeper. He had history teaching positions in New York and Massachusetts and then school principal positions in Ohio and Massachusetts. He later served as superintendent in Scarsdale, New York from 1960 to 1964. In 1965, he became U.S. Commissioner of Education during the Johnson Administration. During his time in that position, he was responsible for carrying out the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, the most extensive federal legislation focused on education, by distributing federal funding to public schools. His duties also concerned upholding provisions of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 by providing federal funding to school districts that proved they did not discriminate based on race.
Howe earned a B.A. from Yale University and a master's degree in history from Columbia University. After leaving the Ford Foundation, he worked as a senior lecturer at the Harvard University Graduate School of Education from 1982 to 1994. A student fellowship and chair at Harvard GSE are named after him. Howe died in 2002.
Arrangement
Arranged in 6 series:
1. Chronological Correspondence.
2. Education and Public Policy.
3. Division of Education and Research.
4. Ford Foundation, General, Bundy Presidency.
5. Ford Foundation, Committees and Task Forces.
6. Other Foundation Divisions.
- Chronological Correspondence, 1971-1981; I; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - Harold Howe II Chrons A-F (1/3), 1971 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons G-N (2/3), 1971 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons O-Z (3/3), 1971 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons A-O (1/2), 1980 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons P-Z (2/2), 1980 (Box 1)
  - Harold Howe II Chrons, 1981 (Box 1)
- Education and Public Policy, 1963-1990; II; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - EPP Program Review (1/6), 1981 (Box 2)
  - EPP Program Review (2/6), 1981 (Box 2)
  - EPP Program Review (3/6), 1981 (Box 2)
  - EPP Program Review (4/6), 1981 (Box 2)
  - EPP Program Review (5/6), 1981 (Box 2)
  - EPP Program Review (6/6), 1981 (Box 2)
  - FY 1980 Education and Public Policy Division (Box 2)
  - EPP -- Grant Making Procedures, 1980 (Box 2)
  - EPP -- Education and Research, 1980 (Box 2)
  - EPP -- PPSO, 1979 (Box 2)
  - EPP -- Resources and Environment, 1980 (Box 2)
  - EPP -- Nutrition Project, 1980 (Box 2)
  - EPP -- Arts, 1980 (Box 2)
  - CUNY-SUNY and New York City Study, Summer 1980 (Box 2)
  - Harold Howe II Speeches and Writings -- Index and 1-10, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Harold Howe II Speeches and Writings -- 11-18, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Harold Howe II Speeches and Writings -- 19-29, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Harold Howe II Speeches and Writings -- 30-42, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Harold Howe II Speeches and Writings -- 43-54, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Harold Howe II Speeches and Writings -- 55-65 (end), 1979-1981 (Box 2)
  - Harold Howe II Permissions, 1973-1980 (Box 2)
  - Index of the Board of Trustees Education Committee Papers, 1967-1990 (Box 2)
  - Index to Education Information Papers submitted to Education Committee and/or full Board of Trustees, 1963-1990 (Box 2)
  - Education for Fun and Profit -- A Report, undated (Box 2)
- Division of Education and Research, 1967-1980; III; 3.94 Cubic Feet 3 record storage boxes
  - HER -- General, 1974-1977 (Box 2)
  - Public Education -- General, 1967-1977 (Box 2)
  - Public Education -- General, 1971-1976 (Box 2)
  - Minorities in Schools, 1972-1978 (Box 2)
  - Minorities in Colleges and Universities, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Women in Schools, Colleges and Universities, 1975-1979 (Box 3)
  - School Finance Reform, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Higher Education -- Policy and Planning, undated (Box 3)
  - Learning Research and Its Application, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - Adolescence, 1977 (Box 3)
  - PPSO -- Humanities, 1975-1978 (Box 3)
  - Public Policy -- General, 1971-1979 (Box 3)
  - Education and Research -- Evaluation, 1973-1976 (Box 3)
  - James W. Armsey Reports, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Education and Research Review leading up to March 1972 Information Paper, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Education and Research -- Planning for Future Education Programs -- FY 1976 and Beyond, undated (Box 3)
  - FF Special Program in Education, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - FF -- Trustee Evaluation of Ford Foundation Future, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Reorganization of Ford Foundation, 1979 July (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation Future Planning -- Keeping the President Informed, 1979 June (Box 3)
  - Presidential Election Review, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation and Women's Programs, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Ethnic Conflict Resolution, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Bi-Lingual Education, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation -- Economic Research Review, 1968-1979 (Box 3)
  - FF -- Program Strategy, 1968-1975 (Box 4)
  - FF -- Trustees (general correspondence), 1968 (Box 4)
  - Ford Foundation and Economic Productivity, 1979 (Box 4)
  - FF -- General, 1969 (Box 4)
  - FF -- General Policies, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Corporate Philanthropy, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
- Ford Foundation, General, Bundy Presidency, 1968-1979; IV; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - FF -- Nutrition Interests, 1979 (Box 4)
  - FF -- Evaluation, 1970 (Box 4)
  - FF -- Dependent Organizations, 1968-1971 (Box 4)
  - FF -- Intern Program, 1974 (Box 4)
  - FF -- Staff Retrenchment, 1975 (Box 4)
  - FF -- Self-Study leading to planning for FY 1973 and Beyond, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - FF -- Self-Study leading to planning for FY 1973 and Beyond, 1972 (Box 4)
- Ford Foundation Committees and Task Forces, 1971-1977; V; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - FF Advisory Management Committee, 1974 (Box 4)
  - FF Advisory Management Committee -- Subcommittee on Staff Planning, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - FF Task Force on Foundation-Employee Relations, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Racial Policy Issues, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
- Other Foundation Divisions, 1967-1977; VI; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - International Division, 1967-1977 (Box 4)
  - Information Papers, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - National Affairs, 1971-1975 (Box 4)